Finding Aid for American Lung Association of Michigan Records, 1944-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Lung Association of Michigan Records
1944-2000
1964-2000
American Lung Association of Michigan.
0496 Bf 2
Organization concerned with the prevention and control of all lung diseases; includes minutes of board of directors and executive committee; correspondence; topical files; and other administrative materials.
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the American Lung Association of Michigan (donor no. 9486 ) and came to the library in July 2004.
The record group is open to research.
The campaign against the principal lung disease of the 19th century, tuberculosis, was originally headed by the Michigan State Board of Health along with the cooperation of sanatoria and local anti-tuberculosis groups in Grand Rapids, Kalamazoo, and Detroit. In 1908, a statewide organization, the Michigan State Association for the Prevention and Relief of Tuberculosis was formed. At the end of 1914, the organization name was changed to the Michigan Anti-Tuberculosis Association and in 1921 to the Michigan Tuberculosis Association. In about 1962, in recognition of the organization's broadening focus, the name was changed to Michigan Tuberculosis and Respiratory Disease Association. There was a subsequent name change in 1973 to American Lung Association of Michigan.
The fight against lung diseases was most effectively engaged at the local level. During the twentieth century associations affiliated with the Michigan Tuberculosis Association were formed in many communities, including Oakland, Wayne and Macomb counties. The American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan resulted from the merger in 1973 of the Tuberculosis and Health Society of Wayne County (incorporated in 1945) with the Macomb County Tuberculosis and Health Association. In 1991, the American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan (which had become independent from the state association) merged into the American Lung Association of Michigan.
The purpose of the current organization is the prevention and control of all lung diseases including pneumonia, emphysema, chronic bronchitis, asthma and tuberculosis through cooperation with patients, the medical community, official and voluntary agencies, community groups and interested citizens.
The record group documents the administration and activities of the American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan up to the merger in 1991 and the statewide association after 1991. The series in the record group are: Background; Early Records; Board of Directors; Executive Committee; Annual Meetings; Publications; Topical Files; Biographical name files; Various reports and other records; Committee files; Chief Executive Officer (Larry McAllister) files; and Correspondence.
Subjects:
American Lung Association of Michigan.; American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan.; Lungs--Diseases--Prevention.; Tuberculosis--Michigan.
Contributors:
American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan.
- Background
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Organizational/background (Box 1)
- Early Records
  - Oakland County Tuberculosis Association, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Tuberculosis and Health Society of Wayne County, 1951-1958 (Box 1)
- Board of Directors
  - Record books
    - 1964-1967, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Meeting files, 1978; 1985-1992 (Box 2)
  - Combined Board of Directors/Executive Committee files, 1997-1999; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Board of Directors files, 8 folders (Box 3)
- Executive Committee
  - Meeting files, 1984-2000 (Box 3)
- Annual meetings
  - 1974-1989 (Box 4)
- Publications
  - Annual reports, 1977-1991 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Topical files
  - Affirmative Action, 1977; 1989 (Box 5)
  - AFSCME Local 308, pulmonary tests, 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - Alpine Air Products vs. Alex Johnson, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - American Lung Association contract, 1990 (Box 5)
  - American Lung Association-Changes in research performance standards, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Animal research, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Asbestos in the schools, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Aspiration of foreign objects in the air (ALAM campaign), 1978 (Box 5)
  - Assets, placement of, 1983-1992 (Box 5)
  - Asthma camps, 1987; 1991 (Box 5)
  - Asthma centers, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Audits, 1978-1982; 1988-1991; 9 folders (Box 5)
  - Bequests, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Bicycle Around Michigan program, 1987-1991 (Box 5)
  - Boilermakers Local 169, screening program, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Breathers Club, 1978-1991 (Box 5)
  - Camp Sun Deer, 1981-1987; 1992; 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Complaints and criticisms
    - General, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Detroit News articles by Douglas Ilka, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Detroit and Wayne County Tuberculosis Foundation, 1969-1984 (Box 5)
  - Freedom from Smoking program, 1981-1989 (Box 5)
  - Future Workers of America program, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Medical Education National Advisory Committee Study, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - Health-O-Rama, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Henry Ford Hospital-Lung Health Study, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Home Air Tests, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Internal Revenue Service (1990 audit) (Box 5)
  - Investment policy (Box 5)
  - Jay Leno Live, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Legislation, 1978 (Box 5)
  - List leasing and exchange, 1984-1991 (Box 5)
  - Membership fulfillment (Box 5)
  - Merger of the American Lung Association of Michigan and the American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan, 1972-1986 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Allergy Society (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Oakland County Tuberculosis Association
    - General, 1971-1982 (Box 5)
    - Merger with American Lung Association of Southeast Michigan, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - Planned giving correspondence, 1988-1992 (Box 5)
  - Pulmonary function testing, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Radon grant, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Radon testing centers, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Respiratory disease program of the Tuberculosis and Health Society of Wayne County, evaluation, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Strategic Planning Retreat, 2000 (Box 5)
  - Sweepstakes, 1992 (Box 5)
  - United Way, 1988-1990 (Box 5)
- Biographical name file of directors, officers, and staff
  - A-Z (3 sequences) (Box 6)
- Various reports and other records
  - Self-Evaluation and other performance evaluation files, 1981-1989; 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Forms, contracts, etc., 1 volumes (Box 7)
  - Management Team meetings, 1 volumes (Box 7)
  - Program of work 1993-1996 (budget 1993-1994) (Box 7)
  - Program Services, Monthly Reports (Box 8)
  - Monthly reports, 1987-1992 (Box 8)
  - Action Plan and Budget, 1979-1994 (with gaps) (Box 9)
  - Action Plan, 1986-1989 (Box 9)
- Committee files
  - Adult Lung Health Committee (Box 10)
  - Allocations Committee (Box 10)
  - Child Lung Health Committee (Box 10)
  - Constituent Relations Committee, 1981-1984 (Box 10)
  - Environmental and Occupational Health Committee (Box 10)
  - Finance Committee, 1993-1999; 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Finance Committee various dates (Box 10)
  - (Ad Hoc) Future Directions Committee (Box 10)
  - Medical Education, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Mutual Concerns Committee (Box 10)
  - Nominating Committee, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Program and Budget Committee, 1984; 1986; 1993-1995; 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Public Information Committee, 1981-1985 (Box 11)
  - Research Committee, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Resource Development Committee, 1978-1984 (Box 11)
  - Resource Development Committee, 1999; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Various (early), 1967-1968 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
  - Committee assignments and charges (Box 11)
  - Board of Directors committee assignments (Box 11)
- Chief Executive Officer (Larry McAllister) files
  - Miscellaneous administrative files (Box 11)
- Correspondence
  (include exchanges with members, board; also mailings)
  - 1988-1990, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - 1994-1995, 2 volumes (Box 13)